Guide to the Brooklyn Navy Yard oral history collection ARC.003
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn Navy Yard oral history collection
1986-2010
2006-2010
Brooklyn Historical Society
Sullivan, Sady
Egan, Jennifer
Romano, Daniella
Filene, Benjamin
Esses, Diane
Brooklyn Navy Yard Development Corporation
ARC.003
2 Linear Feet in 6 boxes.
7.49 Gigabytes in 94 files; Running time (of describe records): 77 hours, 3 minutes, and 53 seconds.
This collection includes oral histories conducted by the Brooklyn Historical Society from 1986 to 1989 as well as oral histories conducted in partnership with the Brooklyn Navy Yard Development Corporation and Brooklyn Historical Society from 2006 to 2010. The interviews were conducted with men and women who worked in or around the Brooklyn Navy Yard and the majority of the interviews are with people who worked in the Yard during World War II. During the interviews, the narrators discuss their lives before working at the Brooklyn Navy Yard, their work at the Brooklyn Navy Yard, their relationships with others in the Yard, and transportation to and from work. While most of the interviews focus on work experiences in and around the Yard, some of the narrators describe gender, racial, and ethnic relations at the Yard and at various neighborhoods in Brooklyn and Manhattan. Many narrators also describe their lives after the Navy Yard.
Box 1
Box 2
Box 3
Box 4
Box 5
Box 6
Box BHS Oral History Box 5
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by narrator's last name.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers with varied restrictions according to narrator agreement. Many oral histories can be accessed onsite at Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library and online at the Oral History Portal.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These oral histories were conducted by Brooklyn Historical Society and Brooklyn Navy Yard Development Corporation staff or consultants over the phone, at Brooklyn Historical Society, and at narrators' homes and businesses from 1986 to 1989 and 2006 to 2010.
Scope and Contents
The Brooklyn Navy Yard oral history collection is comprised of over fifty oral history interviews with men and women who worked in or around the Brooklyn Navy Yard, primarily during World War II. The assembled oral histories in this collection date from 1986 to 2010.
In the interviews, narrators discuss growing up, their work at the Brooklyn Navy Yard, their relationships with others at the Yard, gender relations at the Yard, and transportation to and from work. Many narrators bring up issues of ethnicity, race, and religion at the Yard or in their neighborhoods. Several people describe the launching of the USS Missouri battleship and recall in detail their daily tasks at the Yard. Many of the narrators worked as welders, riveters, office workers, mechanics, electricians, and ship fitters. While the interviews focus primarily on experiences in and around the Yard, many narrators go on to discuss their lives after the Navy Yard, relating stories about their careers, dating and marriage, children, social activities, living conditions and the changes that took place in and around Brooklyn during their lifetimes.
Oral History Note
Oral history interviews are intimate conversations between two people, both of whom have generously agreed to share these recordings with the Brooklyn Historical Society archives and with researchers. Please listen in the spirit with which these were shared. Researchers will understand that:
1. The Brooklyn Historical Society abides by the General Principles & Best Practices for Oral History as agreed upon by the Oral History Association (2009) and expects that use of this material will be done with respect for these professional ethics.
2. Every oral history relies on the memories, views and opinions of the narrator. Because of the personal nature of oral history, listeners may find some viewpoints or language of the recorded participants to be objectionable. In keeping with its mission of preservation and unfettered access whenever possible, BHS presents these views as recorded.
3. Transcripts created prior to 2008 serve as a guide to the interview and are not considered verbatim. The audio recording should be considered the primary source for each interview. It may contain natural false starts, verbal stumbles, misspeaks, repetitions that are common in conversation, and other passages and phrases omitted from the transcript. This decision was made because BHS gives primacy to the audible voice and also because some researchers do find useful information in these verbal patterns.
4. Unless these verbal patterns are germane to your scholarly work, when quoting from this material researchers are encouraged to correct the grammar and make other modifications maintaining the flavor of the narrator's speech while editing the material for the standards of print.
Related Materials
In addition to this collection, Brooklyn Historical Society has other collections with materials related to some of the narrators who appear in the Brooklyn Navy Yard oral history collection. Among these are:
• The Alfred and Lucille Kolkin papers, 1942-1965, ARC.048
• Veronica Kieffer Brooklyn Navy Yard photograph and badge, 1944-1945, V1988.047
• Frank J. Trezza Seatrain Shipbuilding collection, 1861-2011, 1988.016
Historical Note
The origins of the Brooklyn Navy Yard (officially known as the New York Naval Shipyard) date back to 1801, when the United States Navy acquired what had previously been a small, privately owned shipyard in order to construct naval vessels. By the time the Department of Defense ceased shipbuilding activities at the Brooklyn Navy Yard in 1966, eighty-eight vessels had been manufactured at the facility. In 1967, the Brooklyn Navy Yard was acquired by the City of New York and was converted for private commercial use.
The oral history interviews in the collection come from two different collecting efforts one from 1986 to 1989 and another from 2006 to 2010. The interviews dating from 1986 to 1989 were the result of an effort to collect oral histories of Brooklyn residents associated with the Brooklyn Navy Yard and people who lived or worked in Brooklyn prior to the Shellens Gallery of Brooklyn History installation. The effort from 2006 to 2010 was part of the Brooklyn Navy Yard oral history project, a grant funded partnership between Brooklyn Historical Society and the Brooklyn Navy Yard Development Corporation. The goal of the project was to capture the voices of the people who worked at the Yard during World War II and document the evolution of women joining the labor force during the War.
New York Naval Shipyard; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History, Naval; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x History; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; Women welders; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Civilian employees of the United States Armed Forces; World War, 1939-1945 |x War work; Wages |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipfitting; Rivets and riveting; Tailoring |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans; Judaism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Typists; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Oral histories (document genres); Transcripts; Interviews (sound recordings); Video recordings; Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Irish Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; New York Naval Shipyard; Missouri (Battleship: BB 63); Iowa (Battleship); Bon Homme Richard (Aircraft carrier)
- Oral History Interview with Leonard Beck, June 11, 2008; 2010.003.004
  Biographical / Historical
  Leonard Beck (1928- ) grew up in Brooklyn, New York. He was drafted into the Marine Corps in 1952 during the Korean War, after which he became an obstetrician and remained in Brooklyn. Leonard Beck's father, Julius Beck was born in 1894 in Woodhaven, Queens. He ran his own clothing business with his brother, then worked at Brooks Brothers Clothier as a designer cutter until he was asked to work at the Brooklyn Navy Yard during WWII. Following the war, Julius Beck bought into the luncheonette business with his wife.
  Scope and Contents
  During the interview, Leonard Beck (1928- ) focuses on his father's work at the Brooklyn Navy Yard as a tailor. Beck also discusses his own childhood in Brooklyn and how his father made an Eisenhower jacket [military uniform shortened coat] for Franklin Delano Roosevelt. He also mentions American sentiment towards Japanese Americans during the war, the decommissioning of the Brooklyn Navy Yard, Roosevelt's visit to Ebbets Field, and American patriotism. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Conditions Governing Access
  This interview can be accessed onsite at Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library and online at the Oral History Portal.
  Business enterprises; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); East New York (New York, N.Y.); Ebbets Field (New York, N.Y.); Woodhaven (New York, N.Y.); Clothing and dress |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Clothing trade |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Military uniforms; Restaurants; Security systems; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Tailoring |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Wages |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Working class |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; Beck, Julius
- Oral History Interview with Solomon Brodsky, August 6, 1987; 1995.005.002
  Solomon Brodsky (ca. 1905- ) grew up in Brooklyn. After eight years at the Brooklyn Navy Yard, he worked for US Customs until he retired in 1977.
  During the interview, Solomon Brodksy (ca. 1905- ) recalls his work as a packer in the supply depot at the Brooklyn Navy Yard. He was called to service but was given 4F status due to an earlier operation. During his interview, he recalls working long hours, seven days a week, even on Jewish holidays. Brodsky also remembers the launch of the USS Missouri, boxing matches during lunch and the presence of Marine guards for security. He describes the items he packed, including automobiles, the equal treatment of men and women workers and his wages. Interview conducted by Benjamin Filene.
  Ethnicity; Sands Street (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Friendship; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- New York; Local transit -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Religion; Security systems; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Transportation; Wages |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Judaism; World War, 1939-1945; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York Naval Shipyard; Brodsky, Solomon; Missouri (Battleship: BB 63)
- Oral History Interview with Ellen Bulzone, March 20, 2009; 2010.003.005
  Ellen Hanlin Bulzone (1923- ) grew up in Pennville, Indiana on a farm. In 1943, she joined the US Navy with a friend from Indiana, and moved to New York to begin training at Hunter College. After further training and work in Stillwater, Oklahoma and in Sampson, New York, Bulzone was transferred to the Brooklyn Navy Yard in 1946. She married later that year and remained in Brooklyn working at Macy's in Manhattan while her husband served as a commissary officer in California and China. When he returned in 1948, they moved to Norfolk, Virginia, where Ellen Bulzone worked at the Norfolk Navy Yard until her son was born. They later moved to Pensacola Florida, Bayonne, New Jersey and finally Staten Island, New York.
  In this interview, Ellen Hanlin Bulzone (1923- ) details her various duties at the receiving station near the Brooklyn Navy Yard. She also talks about her life before joining the Navy, her uniform, her and her husband's first date at Ebbets Field, her family and in-laws and her marriage inside the Brooklyn Navy Yard Hospital's chapel. She explains how Catholic churches refused to marry them because her husband was Catholic and she was Protestant. She also discusses her feelings about moving from a small town in Indiana to New York City. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan and Jennifer Egan.
  Security systems; Red Hook (New York, N.Y.); Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Naval Base Norfolk (Va.); Pennville (Jay County, Ind.); Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Military uniforms; Wages |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Working class |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Catholics |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ebbets Field (New York, N.Y.); Ethnicity; Transportation -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women |x Education; Friendship; Dating (Social customs); Religion |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York Naval Shipyard; Macy's (Firm); Hunter College
- Oral History Interview with Eleanor Capson, November 3, 2009; 2010.003.006
  Eleanor Beiler Capson (1922- ) grew up in Flatbush, Brooklyn. She attended Erasmus Hall High School and graduated from Brooklyn College in 1942, after which she worked at the US Signal Corps at Fort Monmouth. Capson became a teacher and principal in Brooklyn after leaving the Brooklyn Navy Yard. After retiring, she moved to Riverdale in the Bronx.
  In her interview, Eleanor Beiler Capson (1922- ) explains her work in the materials testing laboratory at the Brooklyn Navy Yard, where she tested the strength of materials used on ships and how to insulate wires used on the ships so they did not mold. She worked at the Brooklyn Navy Yard from January to September of 1943 and was paid a yearly wage, rather than by the hour. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Security systems; Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Military uniforms; Wages |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnicity; Transportation -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women |x Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Armed Forces |x Civilian employees; New York Naval Shipyard
- Oral History Interview with Bettie Chase, September 8, 2010; 2010.003.026
  Bettie Virginia Emory Chase (1922- ) grew up in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, NY. She is African-American and her mother was from Virginia and her father was an orphan. She attended PS42, PS9, and graduated from Girls High in 1940. Bettie worked in the Navy Yard from 1942 to 1946 as a tack welder and later in the Tool Room. She married in 1948 and has three children. Chase was the supervisor of transcriptions for the Episcopal Church in New York for 24 years, from where she retired. She currently works as an organist and choir director at Evening Star Baptist Church in Bedford Stuyvesant.
  In this interview, Bettie Virginia Emory Chase (1922- ) describes how she came to work at the Brooklyn Navy Yard and her experiences as a tack welder and working in the tool room over the next few years. She thinks she was chosen because of her small size, which allowed her to get into small spaces that needed welding. Chase explains that she did not receive much training but was good at tack welding because she has a steady hand. She describes the role of tack welding as similar to a basting stitch in sewing. After six months, Chase was transferred to the Tool Room because of throat problems caused by welding smoke. She goes into detail about her work and coworkers in the Tool Room, including her clothes, time cards, tools, interactions between men and working the night shift (10pm-6am). She also discusses issues and events that took place in the Yard, such as interactions between men and women, sexual assaults, safety concerns, and the overall war effort, which she knew contributed to the deaths of her friends and neighbors. At the end of the interview, Chase talks about her life after the Yard and describes her role as organist and choir director for the Evening Star Baptist Church. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Baptists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Methodist Episcopal Church |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Warships; Navy-yards and naval stations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sex role; Sexual harassment of women -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Welding; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; Evening Star Baptist Church
- Oral History Interview with Clayton Colefield, October 6, 2009; 2010.003.007
  Clayton Colefield (1921- ) was born in Jamaica but grew up in the Bronx. After working for 25 years at the Brooklyn Navy Yard, Colefield taught industrial arts at a high school while earning his bachelor's degree. He eventually moved from the Bronx to Long Island with his family. Following his retirement from teaching, he spent many years traveling with his wife in trailers that he constructed himself. After the death of his wife, Colefield moved to North Carolina.
  During his interview, Clayton Colefield (1921- ) gave detailed accounts of the construction of carriers, destroyers and cruisers at the Brooklyn Navy Yard, as well as repairs made on damaged warships. Because he was able to read blueprints, Colefield was soon promoted to quarterman shipfitter, overseeing other supervisors. Colefield recalls the fatal fire that took place on the USS Constellation (CV-64) when a drum of oil was knocked over into a shaft where welders were working. He also discusses his work on the USS Missouri, the USS Iowa and the USS Wisconsin, for which he was sent to Bayonne, New Jersey to repair. Colefield fondly remembers testing catapults, where the launching pads on the carriers were tested with large weights to see if they could reach a certain speed. He also recollects being invited by a ship captain for a sea trial, when the ship's speed and breaks were tested, as well as and the launching of the USS Missouri. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Bronx (New York, N.Y.); World War, 1939-1945; United States |x Armed Forces |x Civilian employees; New York Naval Shipyard; Missouri (Battleship: BB 63); Iowa (Battleship)
- Oral History Interview with Donald Condrill, December 29, 2006; 2010.003.033
  Donald Richard Condrill (1921- ) grew up in Brooklyn on Sands Street. His father was a plumber and his mother ran a store right outside of the gate of the Brooklyn Navy Yard. Condrill sold newspapers in the marine barracks as a kid and later became the mascot for the basketball and baseball teams before enlisting in 1942. His parents moved away from Sands Street in 1943.
  In this interview, Donald Richard Condrill (1921- ) mostly discusses spending time with the marines and soldiers in the Navy Yard and on Sands Street when he was growing up. He explains that he stopped selling newspapers after less than a year because marines did not want to spend their money on newspapers. He also talks about the neighborhood and the changes that took place during the twenty years that he lived there. Condrill goes on to describe his experience in the Army and his difficulty with color blindness. Interview conducted by Jennifer Egan and Daniella Romano.
  Childhood and youth; Sands Street (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Great Depression |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Marines; Military life; Warships; American newspapers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Waterfronts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard
- Oral History Interview with Helen David, May 7, 2010; 2010.003.027
  Helen Robertson David (1923- ) was born in Montreal, Canada and grew up in Brooklyn. Her father moved to Canada from South Africa and her mother was born in Lithuania in 1890 and came to New York around 1902. David's parents met in Montreal and were prevented from moving to the U.S. in 1925 because there was a cap on immigrants from South Africa [until 1935 a wife lost her American citizenship at that time if her husband was not US citizen]. They were able to move to the US in 1926 and settled in Brooklyn. David attended PS 161, PS 241 in Crown Heights, Junior High 210 and graduated from Erasmus Hall High School in 1939 when she was 16 years old. She attended Brooklyn College as a science major and graduated in 1943. David worked in the Brooklyn Navy Yard in the Sound and Optics Laboratory. She left because she decided to pursue a career in teaching. She got her Master's in education from Teacher's College at Columbia University. David met her husband while attending Brooklyn College. She eventually taught at Valley Stream High School on Long Island for 29 years and has lived in Arizona since 2005.
  Among the many topics Helen Robertson David (1923- ) discusses during this interview are the work she did in the Sound and Optics Lab, memorable events in the Yard such as the building of the USS Missouri and another ship (the Bonhomme Richard), an explosion in the power station, and D-Day. She explains that people were not allowed to quit working in the Yard because it was war time and in order to leave to pursue a teaching career, she had to get permission from the Admiral. She remembers smelling the chocolate factory in the neighborhood while working at the Yard. David discusses gender relations within the Yard and the Lab, telling one story about keeping milk in the Lab's refrigerator; she and the other women would label their milk as if it contained bacteria cultures to keep the men from drinking it. She also talks about her life after the Navy Yard as a woman science teacher in Brooklyn, Manhattan, and Valley Stream (Long Island). Davis is friends with two other interviewees in this collection: Eleanor Capson (2010.003.006) and Mimi (Mildred) Leipzig (2010.003.016). Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Warships; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Teaching; Laboratories; Accidents; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Teachers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Armed Forces |x Civilian employees; United States |x Emigration and immigration; New York Naval Shipyard; Columbia University; Bon Homme Richard (Aircraft carrier); Missouri (Battleship: BB 63)
- Oral History Interview with Angelo DeSalvo, April 28, 2010; 2010.003.028
  Angelo DeSalvo (1931- ) grew up in the Bronx. DeSalvo began working at the Navy Yard in 1955 after serving in the Air Force during the Korean War. Following classes at a Math Institute, he became a radio mechanic and later an electronic mechanic for the Navy ships. He became a supervisor in 1962 and was also a member of the union IBEW Local.